Kerry: I know of and have
used before things like PECS,
communication boards, chat boards,
pod books, and other forms of AAC.
Phil: PECS books, the Pictorial
Exchange Communication System, I
think is what the acronym stands for.
But basically it  is a series
of pictures and then the learner
communicates selecting various
pictures and exchange it with you.
So they're communicating that way.
Zoe: Social stories.
So using visual stories that
explain to a child a situation.
Phil: We also use a lot of
AAC, so Augmentative and
Alternative Communication.
So it might be an iPad and a more
high-tech version of a PECS book with
various symbols, touch the screen
and it verbalises what the symbol
Zoe: The other thing quite related to
that would be comic strip conversations.
So that's another way of explaining
a situation to a child with autism.
It encourages you to look at the
situation from lots of different
perspectives and help them understand
how other people are thinking and
feeling in different situations.
Zoe T: I know that PACS is a speech and
language therapy derived intervention.
And it's very much like intensive
interaction in the sense that
it's follows the child's lead.
RDI also does that to begin with,
but then moves on to enable the
adult guide to lead the child,
but in a declarative sort of way.
Zoe: Using social stories can be really
helpful for children, especially when
they're about to experience a situation
that they've not experienced before.
It can make sure you've taken them
through step by step so that they
can predict what's going to happen.
And they have a better
understanding of it.
It can also explain to them what is
socially acceptable in the situation and
sort of lays it out for them so that they
understand how they're expected to act.
Phil: Again, sometimes that might
seem like, "oh, well, they can speak,
they can do this" or "they can tell
me this", but it's important to model
this is an okay form of communication
so that they can do that and then
thus improve their own communication
through modeling and being, you know,
having the confidence to do that.
Zoe: Comic strip conversations, they're
slightly different in that they're more
about certain situations that the child
may have been in and it helps with talking
through the situation that happened
and making sure you're looking at it
from lots of different perspectives.
Kerry: With our chat boards and at
the moment, we use them to support
like an intensive interaction
time for one of our pupils.
And previously if you had sat down
opposite them and mirrored what they
were doing, you know, lovely recognition
that you were there and there were smiles
and mirroring each other's movements.
But when we introduced the chat boards,
which are just like "point to as you
say" she started making observational
comments about what she can see
around her or how she's feeling.
And there's that social level
of communication with the person
that's supporting, that wasn't there
before and wouldn't be there if
we didn't continue to use the chat
boards, as we communicated with her.